<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<body>

		<b xml:lang="en">Software Development Informations ...</b>
		<b xml:lang="fr">
			Information sur la version actuelle du logiciel ...
		</b>

		<hr />

		<h1 xml:lang="en">What's New</h1>
		<h1 xml:lang="fr">Nouveautés</h1>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			July 2010 : Several bug fixes, adding groovy script support,
			adding importer script in groovy in the editable instuments.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Juillet 2010 : Corrections de bugs, ajout du support de
			script Groovy pour les transformations de fichier midi,
			cartons, ajout de scripts d'import à partir de midi,
			associés à l'instrument. (pour permettre l'import aisé de
			multiples fichiers midi différents)
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">
			June 2010 : Adding an export to movie file button.
			Refactoring Scale Editor for more future improvements on
			gui. Improvements on the paper book rendering. Adding a
			button for exporting the issues in a text file.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Juin 2010 : Ajout d'un export vers fichier video.
			Refactorisation de l'éditeur de gamme, plus simple plus
			ouvert. Amelioration du rendu de type papier (en lecture
			pneumatique).Ajout d'un bouton d'export des problèmes dans
			un fichier texte.
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">
			May 2010 : Fix on Midi output, big fix on adding sample, GUI
			improvements
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Mai 2010 : correction sur l'Output Midi, correction d'un bug
			sur le chargement d'un fichier wav, ameliorations mineures
			d'écrans
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			May 2010 : adding pan support on the middle button. Adding a
			play sub system to send message to external MIDI Interface.
			Printing improvements. Changing the time color in the book
			view. Fix on the encoding in instrument / scale definition.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Mai 2010 : ajout du bouton du milieu pour faire des
			déplacements dans le carton, changement couleur de la couche
			temps. Sous système pour le jeu sur une carte midi (USB ...
			). Correction sur les accents dans la définition des gammes.
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">
			April 2010 : quality improvements in synchronization and
			user feedbacks. adding a search function on instruments.
			adding import scale function in the instrument editor
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Avril 2010 : Q/A, et ajout d'une fonction de recherche
			d'instrument, ajout de l'import des gammes midiboek dans
			l'editeur d'instruments.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			March 26th : reduce large print scale menu in several menus
			+ accelerators + confirm on non saved modification in the
			instrument editor
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			26 Mars : reduction des grands menu d'impression de gamme en
			petits menus + raccourcis claviers + confirmation dans
			l'editeur d'instrument
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">March 13th : Quality improvements</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			13 Mars : Amélioration de la qualité du logiciel
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">
			February - March : Bug Fix and improvements in instrument
			creation ....
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Février - Mars : Correction du divers bugs et amelioration
			sur la création d'instrument (mode loop + ajout
			d'échantillons en masse ... etc ...)
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			10 - Janvier, Amélioration de quelques fonctionnalités.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			January - 23th ,Adding a feed back when the user click on
			the issue panel.
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="fr">
			23 - Janvier, Ajout d'un feedback lorsque l'utilisateur
			click sur une erreur dans le panneau d'erreurs.
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">January - 10th ,functionnalities improving.</p>


		<p xml:lang="fr">
			2 - Janvier, amélioration sur la gestion des fichiers de son
			en interne pour ne pas dupliquer les fichiers et gérer des
			références partagées de fichier son wav. Ajout d'un scroll
			sur l'éditeur de wav.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			January - 2nd ,Improving wav reading, to not duplicate file.
			adding a scroll bar to the wav editing panel.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			1 - Janvier ,Correction d'un bug posant problème sur la
			restitution d'un instrument lorsque celui ci contient un
			grand nombre d'échantillons + améliorations diverses sur
			l'IHM.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			January - 1th , Bug fix on playing instrument with a large
			number of sample. + GUI improvements.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			27 - Decembre, Phase d'optimisation des structures internes.
			La rapidité de chargement a été amelioré de façon
			significative. Correction d'un bug dans le panneau
			d'attente, lorsque les opérations sont rapides.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			December the 27th, Drastic profiling phase on internal
			struture. The loading and search speed has been
			significatively optimized. Bug fixed in the wait panel.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			25 - Decembre, Finalisation repository Web + Edition Local
			d'instrument avec mécanisme de synchronisation. (pour
			permettre de faciliter la contribution sur les instruments)
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			December the 25th, Web Repository Finalization + local
			instrument editing to use the instrument exchange.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			13 - Decembre, Ajout de tous les instruments independemment
			de l'origine de la définition de l'instrument. Présentation
			des instruments sous forme de cover flow.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			December the 13th, adding all the instruments in the gui,
			whenever their origin (local, builting , web ...). Cover
			flow version in beta.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			1 - Decembre, corrections de bugs interne sur l'allocation
			de fichiers temporaires. Ajout d'une fonction d'export de
			gamme sous forme de fichier image.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			December 1th , Bug fixes on the temporary file allocation,
			speed improvements, adding an export as image function for
			the scale.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			14 -Novembre 2009, amelioration sur l'editeur
			d'instrument...
			<br />
			Ajout d'une fonction d'import / export dans le menu fichier.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			Novembrer, 14th 2009, Instrument editor improvements ..
			<br />
			adding import / export function in the file menu.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			13 -Novembre 2009, amelioration des écrans ...

			Ajout d'icones dans l'editeur d'instrument, creation de
			menus pertinents, localisation ...
			<br />
			Ajout d'un outil pour creer des patchs à partir d'un gros
			wav .. (facilite grandement l'utilisation d'un fichier
			monolytique contenant la gamme complète en Wav)
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			November, 13th 2009, GUI Improvements .. adding icones,
			rearranging menus, bug fixes, adding bug reports on main
			functions ...
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			12 -Novembre 2009, bug fixes ...
			<br />
			<ul>
				<li>
					Corrections sur l'éditeur de gamme (pb d'attribution
					sur les pistes)
				</li>
				<li>
					Internationalisation des chaines dans l'interface
					d'edition d'instrument
				</li>
				<li>
					Ajout d'un filtre sur les images dans l'editeur
					d'instrument
				</li>
				<li>
					Envoi de rapport de bugs en asynchrone
					(l'utilisateur n'est plus gêné)
				</li>
			</ul>

		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			Novembrer - 12th 2009, bug fixes ...
			<br />
			<ul>
				<li>
					Fixes on the scale editor (for tracks definitions)
				</li>
				<li>i18n for instrument editor</li>
				<li>
					Adding filter on the image / pictures for the
					instrument
				</li>
				<li>
					asynchonous bug report sending (the gui is not
					freezed)
				</li>
			</ul>
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			11 -Novembre 2009, Ajout d'outil dans d'éditeur de wav pour
			découper les sons. Ajout de boutons supplémentaires pour
			faciliter l'utilisation
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			November 11th - Adding a crop tool in the wav editor to ease
			the use.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			25 - Octobre 2009, travail sur l'editeur d'instrument.
			Augmentation de la performance d'affichage du composant de
			gamme. Ajout de feedbacks sur l'interaction entre le piano
			et la gamme de l'instrument. Ajout d'un état "désactivé" sur
			les touches du piano ne faisant pas partie de la gamme.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			October 25 - 2009, Still working on the instrument editor.
			Speed up the scale rendering. adding feed backs between the
			scale and the the pianoroll. Adding a disable state on the
			pianoroll when the note is not present in the scale.
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="fr">
			24 - Octobre 2009, ajout d'une prévisualisation de l'éditeur
			d'instrument (toujours en cours de construction).
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			October 24 - 2009, Adding a preview of the new instrument
			editor. Still in construction, but for having feedbacks on
			his usability
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			October - Bug Fixes in midi loading / file selected.
			Starting to build online documentation for the software.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Octobre - Bug Fixes / dans le chargement de fichiers midi,
			certaines notes dupliquées dans différentes pistes pouvant
			poser problème lors de la conversion en carton. Ce problème
			est maintenant corrigé. Debut de rédaction de la
			documentation en ligne du logiciel.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			September - Bug Fixes in several places. Back to a 72 dpi
			print, because some printer , or java issue on increasing
			the DPI...
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Septembre - Diverses corrections. retour à une impression en
			72 dpi, sur certaines imprimantes, il y a un pb.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			August 22th 2009 - Adding look and feel menu to change the
			look of the application..
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			22 Aout 2009 - Ajout d'un menu permettant de changer les
			couleurs de la fenetre, si le look "mac" ne convient pas
		</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">August 17th 2009 - Bug fixes ..</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">Aout 2009 - Correction de bugs</p>


		<p xml:lang="en">
			August 2009 - Translation of the drums, pipe stop groups.
			Translation of the scale repository on the web ...
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Aout 2009 - Ajout d'une traduction pour les jeux de tuyaux
			et des percussions. Mise en place sur le web d'un index
			traduit des différentes gammes
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			August 2009 - New Extension Repository to ease the
			installation and update of plugins. Translation of the
			Online Help in both English and French.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Aout 2009 - Une nouvelle fonction dans le menu option,
			permettant de simplifier l'installation et la mise à jour de
			différentes extensions. L'aide en ligne est maintenant dans
			deux langues (Français et Anglais). La traduction dans les
			deux langues de l'apropos ici présent (pour le papa
			d'olivier :-)).
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			19 July 2009 - Adding a translator inside APrint, permitting
			to translate the GUI. Bug Fixes (bug reporter), speedup the
			launch.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">June 2009 - Bug Fixes in several areas</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			June 2009 - Adding a instrument / register controlled preset
			link for the registers sound rendering
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			June 2009 - adding the capability of adding a pipe stop with
			no register controlled
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			June 2009 - Creation of an external repository to manage an
			internet connection, direct modifications of the scales and
			instruments.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			30/05/09 - Bugs fixes in APrint, several improvements
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			22/05/09 - Plugin Isolation to permit on the fly update of
			extensions, adding an automatic update of the extensions
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			21/05/09 - Adding constraints gui to the scale editor,
			adding help extension point for APrint
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			16/05/09 - Adding a import Extension Point on Plugins,
			Plugins are now capable to make transformation on midi files
			before presenting the book, Extension/Plugins enhancements
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			09/05/09 - Adding an OGG export function ..., one bug fix on
			midi loading synchronization, enhancements on GUI
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			01/05/09 - Scale Preview / Export Enhancement, better
			visualization and rendering, adding a scale kind rendering
			(paper ..)
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			14/04/09 - Bug Fixes, GUI enhancement, adding support of Kar
			Files, improvements on the kernel
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			30/03/09 - Correct Toolbars, Fix Bugs thank's to Bug Report.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			15/03/09 - Adding Plugin capablity - for specific
			developments, switch to tabbed view , add automatic restart,
			and automatic playing stop. Adding more preferencies for
			user experience
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			01/03/09 - IHM enhancements, more precision in scale editor.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			28/02/09 - Still Fixes :-), issues previewing ... and so on
			..
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			24/01/09 - Fix a freeze bug while loading / displaying the
			book
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			07/01/09 - Adding a send bug report functionnality. bugs are
			automatically send to the author for improving the feedback
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			29/12/08 - Adding Transition / feedback on the software.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			28/12/08 - Simplify the UI - 3 clicks to listen a file,
			adding a feed back for the errors
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			30/11/08 - Switch to an improved sequencer, soundfont file
			format now supported
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			15/11/08 - Bug fixes and localization of the scale editor
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			11/11/08 - improvements in gamme definition - display all
			characteristics on the paper
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			10/11/08 - Correct a print preferences issue, save the
			pageformat properties, now much more user friendly
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			9/11/08 - Adding Gamme Editor in file menu, bug fixes
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			1/11/08 - 400ko of source code :-) - adding register
			definition, new gamma tool construction
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			26/10/08 - Correct the print preview OutOfMemory Problem,
			now seemlessly usable.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			25/10/08 - English version of the APrint changes
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			09/08 - Adding a scripting language permitting doing the
			instrument translation
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">13/6/08 - Adding instruments to APrint</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			9/5/08 - Change on the image instrument size
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">4/5/08 - Add the file name in the print</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">1/5/08 - Updating the help content</p>
		<p xml:lang="en">
			29/4/08 - Add an image to the instrument, adding a help
			section
		</p>
		<h1>Contact</h1>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			You can contact us a this email adress
			<a href="mailto:frett27@free.fr">frett27@free.fr</a>
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Vous pouvez nous contacter à cette adresse mail :
			<a href="mailto:frett27@free.fr">frett27@free.fr</a>
		</p>


		<h1>APrint License</h1>

		<center>
			<b>APrint - Copyright (C) Patrice Freydiere 2005-2008</b>
		</center>

		<pre>
			This library is free software; you can redistribute it
			and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public
			License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
			version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
			version.



			This library is distributed in the hope that it will be
			useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied
			warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
			PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more
			details.


			You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public
			License along with this library; if not, write to the Free
			Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330,
			Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.
		</pre>


		<h2>
			This software include Liquid Look And Feel - under LGPL
			License
		</h2>

		<h2>This software include Gervill, under GPL License</h2>

	</body>
</page>